ערב טוב. Erev Tov. Today's דף Daf is י"ט Yud Tet 19
and we pick up with four lines from the top of י"ט
עמוד א' Yud Tet Amud Aleph and the current discussion, the current
issue under discussion is when a נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei, very simple
question, right, the פסוקים Psukim talk about a נזיר, Nazir, a normal
נזירות, Nezirut, started off טהור, Tahor, not like the case in the
accepting נזירות Nezirut in a cemetery, became טמא, Tamei, goes and does
the whole sprinkling on three and seven, shaving the hair on day
seven, a special thing for נזיר, Nazir, bringing the קרבנות Korbanot on
day eight, תורה Torah says you restart the נזירות, Nezirut, simple question,
when do you restart the נזירות? Nezirut? Four opinions.
One is רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda that says
on day seven, that's the day you became טהור. Tahor. רבי Rabbi
who says on day eight, as soon as it's the time that
fits to bring the קרבן, Korban, whether that is the night or
the day of day eight depends on your general approach about whether
you think the nighttime is considered to be like even if practically
you can't bring it, the time has arrived vis-a-vis the קרבנות. Korbanot.
And then two other positions, the position of חכמים Chachamim in a
ברייתא Braisa that say that only after you bring the חטאת, Chatas,
and then a position of רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקא Rabbi Yishmael b'no shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka that says, excuse
me, רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yishmael b'no
shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka that says only after bringing the חטאת
Chatas and the אשם. Asham. The only thing you don't have to
do is bring the עולה. Olah. And some of those positions are
learned out from וקדש את ראשו ביום ההוא, Vikiddash et rosho bayom
hahu, that day, the day is significant without necessarily all of the
קרבנות. Korbanot. רבי Rabbi says without any of the קרבנות Korbanot and
חכמים Chachamim say without the עולה Olah suffices and רבי ישמעאל בנו
של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yishmael b'no shel Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka says pretty much you need the קרבנות, Korbanot, the one thing
you don't need is the עולה. Olah. Okay. And now the גמרא
Gemorah picks up four lines from the top on י"ט עמוד א'.
Yud Tet Amud Aleph. מאן תנא להא דתנו רבנן? Man tanna leha
detanu rabbanan? Who is the author, the תנא Tanna from those that
we've been discussing of that which our רבנן Rabbanan taught? And here's
what the רבנן Rabbanan taught: אשה שנדרה בנזיר, Isha shenadra binazir, a
woman takes a vow to be a נזירה, Nazira, ונטמאה vinitme'ah and
she became טמאה tme'ah and then we're supposed to assume here from
the ongoing conversation is that she sanctified her two birds, one for
חטאת Chatas and one for an עולה, Olah, okay, which she would
bring when her טומאה tuma was done. ואחר כך הפר לה בעלה,
Ve'acharkach heifer lah ba'alah, and the husband, always a little too little
too late, comes along and he הפר heifer for her after she
became טמאה, tme'ah, again and presumably at least the way תוספות Tosafot
read it, after she sanctified the קרבן, Korban, maybe not, but that's
the way תוספות Tosafot read it.
Still on the same day?
No,
he הפר heifer on the day that he heard, but it doesn't
have to be the same day that she took it. He הפר
heifer ביום שמעו, beyom sham'o, that he heard about it,
that she said
it, exactly.
He doesn't have to hear her say it.
Correct. He has to hear that she said, oh, I took the
following נדר. Neder. Exactly.
Isn't it strange that he didn't hear this by now?
She's already letting her hair grow, she's taking, yeah I don't know,
so maybe it is on the same day. It could all be
on the same day, it could all be two days later, but
whatever it is, okay. Now, so basically what's her status right now?
She's no longer a נזירה Nazira but she had been a נזירה
Nazira who became טמאה, tme'ah, who was obligated in קרבנות. Korbanot. Does
she still bring the קרבנות? Korbanot? Not
normally you have the נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei bring the קרבן. Korban.
Here you have somebody that is a non-נזיר Nazir bringing קרבנות Korbanot
because they were a נזיר טמא. Nazir Tamei. Normally you can't get
to that state, you can't stop being a נזיר Nazir until you
go through this whole process, but this woman managed now to be
a non-נזיר Nazir who actually was a נזירה טמאה Nazira Tme'ah and
obligated in קרבנות. Korbanot. What does she do? Yes.
Is נזירות Nezirut always considered to be a type of נדר? Neder?
It is, yeah.
I mean, it is true sometimes usually the ברייתא Braisa נדרה, נזר,
nadra, nazar, right, but it's all like, yeah, I mean all the
things of הפרה, hafara, התרה. hatara. Now there are some ways in
which it's really a subset of a
נדר, Neder,
like what issues did we discuss that might be different for נזירות?
Nezirut? Questions about maybe questions if you make it based on a
תנאי, tenai, maybe there's special requirements that נזירות Nezirut can't be based
on a תנאי tenai in ways a נדר Neder can. So there
might be like, it might be a subset, but it is a
type of a נדר, Neder, absolutely. And I mean it's the
פסוק, pasuk, right, איש
או אשה כי יפלי לנדור נדר נזיר.
Ish o isha
ki yafli lindor neder nazir. So it actually uses the word יפלי
yafli which is the technical הלכתית halachic term of הפלאה, hafla'ah, which
is a speech act, and לנדור נדר נזיר. lindor neder nazir. Okay,
but it's like a subset of נדר. Neder. All right, so here
what does she do, this woman in this interesting state? So אמר
רב, Amar Rav, מביאה חטאת העוף ואינה מביאה עולת העוף. mavia chatas
ha'of ve'aina mavia olas ha'of. So the ברייתא Braisa says she brings
the חטאת Chatas and not the עולה. Olah. So that's an interesting
position. So clearly we see that even though she's no longer a
נזירה, Nazira, she still brings the קרבנות Korbanot that she was obligated
in. Okay, that makes sense, she was obligated, even though her status
stopped now, she did violate, she was a נזירה טמאה, Nazira Tme'ah,
she was obligated in those, which is interesting which is basically also
saying that the bringing of the קרבן Korban are not necessarily part
of a process of beginning the new נזירות Nezirut of טהרה, Tahara,
right? The bringing of the קרבן, Korban, right, they do two things.
They deal with the fact that you violated your נזירות, Nezirut, whether
willingly or unwillingly, right? And... Therefore they deal with the past, but
they're also future-oriented. They also deal with beginning the new status. So
this woman, right, she, you could say, okay, it's interesting, so she
still brings the קרבנות korbanot because she still violated in the past
or whatever, even if she didn't intentionally do it, her נזירות nezirut
status had been violated and therefore she brings it even though it's
not about beginning a new process. Okay, very interesting type of a
situation. But interesting, so תוספות Tosfot adds again, which is not in
this ברייתא, braita, that she already sanctified the animal, which might therefore
mean like, okay, like you're already like obligated to bring it, so
maybe if you didn't sanctify it we would say do nothing, but
that's not clear in the ברייתא. braita. Okay, now, but what is
interesting is that it splits it, it says she brings the חטאת
chatat and not the עולה, olah, and anyway doesn't even just address
the issue about the אשם, asham, so you know, how do you
understand that? Like you could speculate she's bringing the stuff that's past-oriented
and not the stuff that's future-oriented the way I tried to set
it up, but why would the עולה olah of all things be
the thing that is future-oriented, right? Because the עולה olah usually is
pretty inconsequential to her status or to starting a new status, so
it's a fascinating case, but it's hard to understand this split of
bringing the חטאת chatat not bringing the עולה. olah. Yes, Charlie.
And she could still bring an עולה olah as a voluntary.
Yes, that is true, but that's why, so let me put that
on the table right away. Anybody can bring an עולה, olah, what's
the big deal? So that's partly why תוספות Tosfot says she's already
sanctified the birds, not necessarily to say that she brings a חטאת,
chatat, maybe she would bring that even if she hadn't sanctified anything
because, you know, she had had that state. But תוספות Tosfot says
an עולה, olah, if she hadn't sanctified anything, just sanctify a bird
as an עולה olah now, you're not a נזיר, nazir, why not?
The problem was it was sanctified as an עולת נזיר olat nazir
and she is no longer נזיר, nazir, so that puts that bird
that's an עולה olah in that strange status. A סתם עולה stam
olah she could bring, but the bird that was an עולת נזיר
olat nazir she can't bring because she's not a נזיר. nazir. Now,
why not is not clear, so that's what we're going to try
to figure out, but let's first take the other questions. Yes.
Two questions: one, separate from נזיר, nazir, if somebody becomes טמא tamei
from the dead they have to go through this process anyway.
Not with קרבנות, korbanot, just sprinkling the ashes, right.
Second question is, is there a possibility that when the husband revokes
the vow of נזירות nezirut it becomes retroactively as if it never
happened?
Yeah, so that's exactly the question the גמרא Gemara is going to
ask. We normally have assumed in all of מסכת נדרים, Masechet Nedarim,
and you're anticipating the גמרא, Gemara, that when you go to a
בית דין Beit Din and do a התרה hatarah then it never
happened. When the husband does a הפרה hafarah like an annulment, that
really it had happened and he just sort of stops it from
this point forward and doesn't retroactively. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara is
actually about to ask that question. If it really were retroactive completely
then you couldn't begin to understand why she's bringing a חטאת, chatat,
right? But let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. Yeah.
What's the purpose of an עולה olah in general? What's its function?
Yeah, I mean that's a general question, I mean is a normal
עולת נדר, olat neder, is it just סתם stam a gift, the
גמרא Gemara said before, דורון בעלמא? doron be'alma? Is it also some
sense of, like the גמרא Gemara also tries to also connect it
in ways to sin-related issues, so it's to be מכפר mechaper for
like not doing מצוות עשה mitzvot aseh or מכפר mechaper for הרהורי
עבירה, hirhurei aveirah, you know? But that's like I would say not
necessarily the פשט, pshat, but that is a way in putting it
in some of the more marginal role in terms of חטא. chet.
In types of these things which are more status-related than sin-related, it's
not clear, although it seems that the function sort of is, is
that it's a way of now like making up, you know, it's
sort of like we fixed the bad and now we're sort of
like, you know, doing an act of goodwill to sort of like
get things started again on a good foot, type of an idea.
Like so, the חטאת chatat and the אשם asham sort of fix
the mess that was made and now, and here's a little gift,
God, and let's get started again. So something of that nature. But
it's hard to understand exactly functionally what the עולה olah does and
that's why the גמרא Gemara calls it a דורון בעלמא. doron be'alma.
All right, so now let's see, so we have this very interesting
status of yes חטאת chatat and no עולה, olah, and which is
bizarre, right? If, you know, עולה olah should be the thing that's
most easy to bring, as Charlie asked. So let's take a look.
So who is that תנא? tanna? אמר רב חסדא רבי ישמעאל היא.
amar Rav Chisda Rabbi Yishmael hi. It's רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. Okay,
now what does this have to do with רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael?
All רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said is, if you remember, that when
a נזיר nazir starts again he only starts after bringing the חטאת
chatat and the אשם. asham. Okay, other people said he starts even
with less than that, just the חטאת, chatat, even before bringing any
קרבנות, korbanot, right? So what does any of this thing have to
do with רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael?
If it's to give weight to the חטאת, chatat, so other positions
gave weight to the חטאת. chatat. The חכמים Chachamim say you only
start again once you bring a חטאת. chatat. So what's interesting? So
תוספות Tosfot says, get your head around this, that it's because רבי
ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael beRabbi Yossi excluded the עולה. olah. So
why does that tell you? Because he needed a פסוק pasuk to
exclude an עולה. olah. All the other תנאים tannaim said an עולה
olah of course doesn't do anything, it's meaningless—so I mean, not I
mean whatever—but it's not related to the world of the נזיר, nazir,
so you don't even need a פסוק pasuk to exclude it. He
said no, the thing that the פסוק pasuk ביום ההוא bayom hahu
is excluding. is an עולה olah because I might have thought that
the עולה olah was necessary to actually begin the counting. So that's
just for him, he is the one תנא tanna that sees the
עולה olah having some potentially functional role in the world of נזיר.
nazir. So he's the one that could say this woman who was
a נזיר nazir and isn't a נזיר nazir can't bring this עולת
נזיר. olas nazir. Again, that's why תוספות Tosafot says he already sanctified
the bird because it got labeled as an עולת נזיר. olas nazir.
So everybody else would say, what do I care it labeled as
an עולת נזיר? olas nazir? All it is is an עולה, olah,
it doesn't have any functional role in the world of a נזיר.
nazir. Yeah, the נזיר nazir brings it, but it's just an עולה.
olah. So you're not a נזיר? nazir? Still bring it. What do
I care? Okay, whereas רבי ישמעאל ברבי אלעזר Rebbi Yishmael beRebbi Elazar
says no, no, no, it still is somehow playing some type of
role in that world, not a role that prevents you from starting
again, but some type of a role. And now that you're not
a נזיר, nazir, you can't bring the עולת נזיר olas nazir anymore.
Okay, that's great. But if you can't bring the עולה, olah, how
do you even begin to think you could bring the חטאת, chatas,
right? Which is much more central. So that's the question the גמרא
Gemara is going to ask. Okay, let's take a look. So it
says like this: מאי קסבר, mai kasavar, where am I? Here. מאי
קסבר, mai kasavar, now what is he holding? אי קסבר בעל מעקר
עקר, ei kasavar baal meaker aker, here's your question, David. If he
holds that the husband
retroactively uproots when he does a הפרה, hafara, חטאת גופא נמי לא
לייתי. chatas gufa nami lo laysei. How can you bring a חטאת?
chatas? This woman was never a נזירה. nezira. Okay. אי קסבר בעל
מיגז גייז, ei kasavar baal meigez gaiaz, if he thinks that the
husband only cuts it off, you know, it was good until now
and then he chops it off from this point on, so which
is what we normally assume, so עולת גופא נמי לייתי. olas gufa
nami laysei. So bring an עולה olah because this woman was a
full נזירה nezira who became טמאה, temeiah, she's not that status now,
but she had that status when she was, and therefore let her
bring the עולה. olah. So I still don't understand why you can
bring a חטאת chatas and not bring an עולה. olah. So the
גמרא Gemara says: לעולם קסבר בעל מעקר עקר. leolam kasavar baal meaker
aker. Now this is a very amazing position shift the גמרא Gemara
takes, I mean, because as I said, the assumptions through all מסכת
נדרים Masechet Nedarim is that a husband only cuts it off from
this point onwards. Here the גמרא, Gemara, at least to work with
this ברייתא, braisa, it's not saying that this is the הלכה, halacha,
but at least to work with this ברייתא, braisa, is saying that
this ברייתא braisa is assuming the husband retroactively undoes it. Now, besides
the fact that that's not how we פסקן pasken by הפרה, hafara,
we don't פסקן pasken it's retroactive, that would seem to be the
hardest position. Because if retroactively she wasn't a נזירה, nezira, how can
you begin to think you bring a חטאת? chatas? Right? It's much
more interesting to think she was a נזירה, nezira, she's not anymore,
and somehow some קרבנות korbanos she brought for the past and other
קרבנות korbanos are related to the future, something like I was saying.
That's much more interesting, I think, and it can explain why you're
bringing a חטאת. chatas. But if you say she never was a
נזירה nezira retroactively, how is she bringing a חטאת? chatas?
In other words, if it's legally a type of הפקעת נזירות? hafkaas
nezirus?
Mm-hmm, exactly. The same logic.
Exactly. So let's see what it says. So if it's retroactive, how
could you think that she brings a חטאת? chatas? So the גמרא
Gemara says: רבי ישמעאל סבר לה כרבי אלעזר הקפר, Rebbi Yishmael savar
lah keRebbi Elazar HaKappar,
and he holds like רבי אלעזר הקפר. Rebbi Elazar HaKappar. דתניא, detanya,
we saw in a ברייתא: braisa: רבי אלעזר הקפר ברבי אומר, Rebbi
Elazar HaKappar beRebbi omer, רבי אלעזר הקפר Rebbi Elazar HaKappar says, מה
תלמוד לומר, mah talmud lomar, what is meant by the verse: וכפר
עליו מאשר חטא על הנפש? vechiper alav measher chata al hanefesh?
This is about the נזיר טמא, nazir tamei, right? And he brings
these things, these sacrifices, and he is atoned because he has sinned
on the נפש. nefesh. So is the נפש, nefesh, by the way,
the soul in his soul or is the נפש nefesh the body
that he encountered? Right? So anyway, but it's clearly talking about becoming
טמא. tamei. But רבי אלעזר הקפר Rebbi Elazar HaKappar interprets this more
broadly. No, so he says, what does it mean he sinned? וכי
באיזו נפש חטא זה? vechi beeizo nefesh chata zeh? Against what soul
did he sin? אלא שציער עצמו מן היין. ela shetsier atsmo min
hayayin. He sinned against his own soul that he withheld from himself
wine. Now, this is of course a very creative interpretation for a
couple of reasons. First of all, I guess because we're coming close
to יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, let's talk about the word נפש nefesh
for a minute. כי כל הנפש אשר תעונה, ki kol hanefesh asher
teuneh, ועניתם את נפשתיכם. veinithem es nafshoseichem.
So the verses that talk about fasting on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
use specifically the word נפש, nefesh, soul, you should afflict your soul.
Now normally when we think about נפש, nefesh, right, we think about
like something spiritual. Okay, but
when it speaks about
the animals though, it says like: כל נפש אשר הוא חי, kol
nefesh asher hu chai, לכם יהיה לאכלה, lachem yihyeh leochlah, שבעים נפש.
shivim nefesh.
Well, that's right, exactly. So in the תורה Torah it means much
more about life than it does mean about like some type of
a soul, number one. But specifically about ועניתם את נפשתיכם, veinithem es
nafshoseichem,
some biblical scholars say that, ready? That I think if I got
this right, the Akkadian cognate—now I have to know what both the
word Akkadian and cognate mean—the Akkadian cognate of the word נפש nefesh
actually means throat. And that it actually has something to do with
the sort of appetite. Okay? So therefore, כי כל הנפש אשר תעונה,
ki kol hanefesh asher teuneh, ועניתם את נפשתיכם, veinithem es nafshoseichem,
somehow connects directly to this sense of pleasure and withholding sort of
pleasure and food from yourself. That's a way they try to understand
that that might be like, you know, a more clear in the
פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. It's talking specifically about fasting. So
I mentioned that here because Rashi says: Which נפש nefesh did he
sin against? He sinned against his נפש nefesh for not drinking wine,
but it's something very much having to do with pleasure and eating
and appetite. Number one. I don't know if that was his intent,
but that is interesting in terms of the word נפש. nefesh. The
other thing that's interesting is that again he focuses on the idea
of denying yourself, self-denial.
And that is a lot of how people think what is a
נזירות nezirut about? It's about asceticism and self-denial. Now this point we
discussed before, a נזיר nazir could go ahead and
he could drink, he could eat fatty meat, and he could do
all types of things, he could have sex, he could do all
types of things, right? So it's just wine. So we should say
wine makes the נזירות nezirut about asceticism? So more פשט pshat would
be that it's rather because wine of its intoxicating powers, not because
of its pleasure prowess, that is a problem. So he is framing
it that what נזירות nezirut is about, or at least the problem
with נזירות, nezirut, is the ascetic aspect that comes, the denial aspect
that comes from the wine, which is again, not necessarily פשט. pshat.
And then of course the third thing is, he's taking a פסוק
pasuk that's about טומאה tumah and applying it generally to the idea
of נזיר. nazir. So this is his approach and look, we've seen
approaches even more dominant approaches and I mentioned this before in נדרים
nedarim that spoke about how problematic it was to take a נדר.
neder. What's interesting is that the גמרא gemara is sort of less
condemning, seems to be in my view, less condemning of being a
נזיר nazir than it did about just making random נדרים. nedarim. Okay,
so there are negative voices but they're not as loud and as
dominant. So here anyway the גמרא gemara introduces this. There's a חטא
chet that you do by becoming a נזיר. nazir. Now okay, big
deal. You did a חטא chet by being a
נזיר. nazir. Big deal in this context. Big deal in this context.
How does that say that you bring the חטאת chatas of a
נזיר? nazir? Right? If I did some sin like a חטא שציער
עצמו מן היין, chet shetzi'er atzmo min hayayin, if I decided to
take a תענית, ta'anis, right? And רבי אלעזר's rabbi eliezer because the
end of רבי אלעזר הקפר's rabbi eliezer hakapar line is and you
can make a קל וחומר kal vachomer ומה זה שלא ציער עצמו
אלא מן היין umah zeh shelo tzi'er atzmo ela min hayayin this
guy only denied himself wine ומה זה שלא ציער עצמו אלא מן
היין umah zeh shelo tzi'er atzmo ela min hayayin this guy only
denied himself wine
נקרא חוטא nikra chotei he's called a sinner המצער
עצמו מכל דבר hametza'er atzmo mikol davar somebody who denies himself everything
meaning you take a תענית ta'anis that you don't have to take
על אחת כמה וכמה al achas kama vekama how much more so
are you a sinner? Right? And this is the question in the
גמרא, gemara, this part of a larger discussion in the גמרא, gemara,
whether somebody who takes a is the תענית ta'anis is נקרא קדוש
nikra kadosh or נקרא חוטא. nikra chotei. Right? Which is very much
this question about is it good to try to separate from the
physical pleasures and so on. So he says you're a sinner. Okay,
so if I went ahead and I took a תענית ta'anis and
I didn't have to, according to רבי אלעזר הקפר, rabbi eliezer hakapar,
would he tell me I have to bring a חטאת? chatas? Of
course not, right? I can't bring a חטאת chatas just because I
did something that's considered to be some vague type of a sin,
right? It has to be a very specific concrete עבירה, aveirah, you
know, that you're חייב כרת chayav kareis for etc. So it was
very nice that he says that this is some moral sin here
or some religious sort of sin without being a technical עבירה. aveirah.
How does that explain why this person, the woman, if retroactively she
was never a נזירה, nezirah, retroactively she was never a נזירה nezirah
according to this approach, why is she bringing a חטאת? chatas? So
תוספות tosafos says that's why תוספות tosafos says we're talking that she
already sanctified the animal. Because she's already got this bird, the חטאת
העוף chatat ha'of sitting there. So since that already exists, that it's
been sanctified now of course it does raise an interesting question. Could
you say if retroactively she wasn't a נזירה, nezirah, then retroactively when
she sanctified it, she was a non-נזירה nezirah who was sanctifying it
and if you're not a נזיר, nazir, can you sanctify an animal
as a חטאת נזיר? chatat nazir? All right, whatever. But anyway, let's
assume that it does have that sanctity. So it's got bird's got
this sanctity. So now can we offer it? So because it's already
sanctified, we don't sanctify it, we'd rather have to let it die
or whatever. And the question is can we offer it? We're willing
to rely on weaker justifications essentially. And added to this is an
idea that although you never bring a חטאת chatas unless you are
clearly obligated to bring it, an exception to this rule is the
חטאת העוף. chatat ha'of. For example, a woman who miscarried and does
not know if the fetus was viable or not. Is she a
יולדת? yoledes? Is she obligated to bring this קרבנות korbanos of a
יולדת? yoledes? She cannot stay in this
limbo because then she'll never be able to enter into the בית
המקדש. beis hamikdash. You say don't bring a sacrifice, it might be
חולין בעזרה, chullin ba'azarah, maybe you're not obligated. Right? Okay, but if
you don't bring a sacrifice then she'll never finish become טהורה tehorah
and then don't eat a קרבן, korban, don't go to the בית
המקדש beis hamikdash cause maybe you're טמאה teme'ah and maybe therefore you
haven't finished your process. So she's going to remain in limbo her
whole life. So we have a tradition, מסורה, mesorah, that the woman
actually, מסורה mesorah that the woman actually can bring a חטאת העוף
על הספק. chatat ha'of al hasafek. She can bring the bird sacrifice
for a יולדת yoledes even though she's in a state of doubt.
Normally we would never allow that. So that introduces this idea that
a חטאת העוף, chatat ha'of, not other חטאות, chataos, but a bird
חטאת chatat can sometimes be brought even in a case of doubt.
Now there is a difference between doubt and bringing something for... Questionably
justifiable reasons. You know what I'm saying? One is like you might
really be obligated, we're not sure. The other is yeah, there's some
reason why it might make sense to bring it, you know? But
nevertheless, that's what we're saying. There's a little more flexibility with bringing
a חטאת העוף. chatas ha-of. So what we have said now is,
this woman retroactively wasn't a נזירה, nezira, but you got this bird
here that's sanctified as a חטאת chatas and you gotta figure out,
are we just gonna not do anything, let it die, whatever, can
we do something with it? Well, if the bird's a חטאת העוף
chatas ha-of and there was an element of sin in you having
vowed as a נזיר nazir and having denied yourself wine, even though
halachically you weren't a נזיר, nazir, but there was some element of
sin going on in that process, that's enough of a justification to
bring the חטאת. chatas. Very strange conclusion if you ask me. תוספות
Tosfos of course asks: Let's say she never became טמאה. temeiah. If
that's true, then a woman who accepted נזירות, nezirus, never became טמאה,
temeiah, her husband sanctified an animal as a חטאת, chatas, her husband
annulled her vow retroactively, if we're assuming it's retroactive, let her still
bring a חטאת chatas because there was this element of sin? So
תוספות Tosfos says: Ah, here's the thing. If she had never become
טמאה, temeiah, then she doesn't bring a bird חטאת, chatas, she brings
a בהמה behemah as a חטאת. chatas. And a בהמה behemah as
a חטאת chatas cannot be brought doesn't have this latitude, doesn't have
this idea of ספק safek and even if it's not definitely obligated.
So the כלל klal is, yeah, there's a כלל. klal. The כלל
klal is that
a בהמה behemah doesn't come on a ספק. safek.
The real כלל klal is that the only thing that's a ספק
חטאת safek chatas is a bird. So therefore, that's why תוספות Tosfos
says, because this is a vague sense that she did something wrong
and she had been a נזיר nazir even though retroactively she isn't,
if she's got a bird חטאת, chatas, which is the only thing
you'll get as a נזיר nazir which you can only get as
a נזיר טמא, nazir tamei, נזירות טמאה, neziras temeiah, then that would
still be appropriate to bring. Very, very complicated and very weird also,
that that's sufficient justification. Okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara answer. Now,
why doesn't she bring an עולה? olah? So this is even stranger.
חטאת chatas is normally the thing that requires the most clear
obligation in order to bring. You don't just סתם stam bring a
חטאת chatas because you want. But now what we're saying is, well,
if the עולה olah had not really been identified as part of
the world of the נזיר, nazir, of course you could bring any
עולה olah you want. But because this is the opinion that sees
עולה olah somehow important in the נזירות nezirus process, the נזירות קרבנות,
nezirus korbanot, they do play some role, right? That's what we said
because it had to be excluded shows that it plays some role.
And because we don't have a sense that, you know, we don't
have any justification to bring the עולה olah as a נזיר, nazir,
because retroactively she isn't a נזיר. nazir. The only thing we can
justify is something relating to the fact that there was some sin
involved. But bringing an עולה olah as a נזיר, nazir, you know,
or an עולה olah of a נזיר nazir has no way to
be justified. If it was a pure עולה olah you could bring
it. If it was weightier and it was a חטאת chatas you
could bring it because there's some sense of חטא cheit involved, but
in this middle ground, there's no justification. Very, very strange answers. That's
how the גמרא Gemara explains this. Now, to finish this, it says
the גמרא Gemara just says one question about רבי אליעזר הקפר. Rabbi
Eliezer HaKappar. It says like this:
והא בנזיר טמא כתיב. Ve-ha be-nazir tamei kesiv. That verse that רבי
אליעזר הקפר Rabbi Eliezer HaKappar learns to say that a נזיר nazir
is a sinner is talking only about a נזיר טמא. nazir tamei.
How could you make a general principle that self-denial and asceticism is
a sin, then why would it only be talking about a נזיר
טמא? nazir tamei? ואנן אפילו נזיר טהור קאמרינן. Ve-anan afilu nazir tahor
kamrinan. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer applies his idea even by a
נזיר טהור. nazir tahor. How can he do that? Gemara says, קסבר
רבי אליעזר הקפר נזיר טהור נמי חוטא הוא. Kasar Rabbi Eliezer HaKappar,
nazir tahor nami chotei hu. No,
you know what? It's true. He thinks that this idea that you're
a חוטא chotei applies even to a נזיר טהור nazir tahor to
limit it to that case.
דהיינו טעמא דכתיב בנזיר טמא, De-hainu ta'ama de-chsiv be-nazir tamei, אשר חטא
על הנפש, asher chata al ha-nefesh, הוה ושנה בחטא. hoveh ve-shoneh be-cheit.
Because he like doubled the sin, meaning he was so negligent, either
you could say it just means he stretched on his נזירות, nezirus,
he allowed himself to become טמא tamei and therefore he stretched it
on, or you could say that it reflects how there was even
less justification for him to become a נזיר. nazir. If he was
now again, sometimes accidents happen, but as a general point,
often accidents don't just happen. You know, sometimes they do, but sometimes
there's a sense that we could have been more careful, right? So
isn't that famous story about the guy who was like, I don't
know, this golf pro or whatever, I
mean this world expert golf player, and there he was, he would
practice like 13, 14 hours a day. Anyway, there he was, he
was
hitting golf balls or whatever, like every single swing he was getting
almost every single one was like a hole-in-one. And this guy who's
watching him said, wow,
you are really lucky. He says, yeah, you know what? And the
more I practice, the luckier I get.
So okay, so accidents happen, but the more you're careful, the fewer
those accidents happen anyway.
So anyway, so that could be the idea of שונה בחטא, shoneh
be-cheit, meaning either it's just you've extended... extended it, or B, you
know, it shows that there's even, was even less justification for you
having chosen this type of a path.
And that's, yeah, so the פסוק pasuk is talking about נזיר טמא,
nazir tamei, the idea that נזיר טהור nazir tahor is a problem,
he doesn't get from the פסוק. pasuk. Right.
He gets from his read of the פסוק. pasuk. I understand that
it's calling him a חוטא chote not because of the טומאה tumah
per se, because my read of this verse is that fundamentally everyone
was a חוטא, chote, but it's laying it on him because he
really, you know, you know, showed his irresponsibility of adoption this. Yeah,
but not because of his טומאה. tumah. He's saying the טומאה tumah
just demonstrates how much he's really, you know, how deeply problematic it
was that he became a general נזיר. nazir. So that's the point,
that even though it's about, even though it's in the case of
טומאה, tumah, it's not about him being טמא. tamei. Okay.
Okay. So תוספות Tosafot just says the first explanation, which I think
is a little less פשט. pshat. Four lines down in the wide
lines. Fine, the טעמא דכתיב קרבן נזיר הוא ושנה בחטא שלא נזהר
מטומאה והאריך צער על צערו ta'ama dechtiv korban nazir hu veshana bechet
shelo nizhar mitumah veherich tzar al tza'aro מלהנות ביין. milehanot beyayin.
He stretches it out longer than necessary. Okay, but again I would
say more because it even undermines it any more of a claim
to a justification of that it was really, you know, really meant
something to be a נזיר, nazir, if it really meant something you
wouldn't have been, you know, you wouldn't have allowed yourself to become
טמא. tamei. Okay, one way or the other. Anyway, to me that's
the גמרא Gemara takes the approach that was retroactive, has you bring
a חטאת העוף chatat ha'of on a very little basis. To me
it would have been much more interesting to say that it was
מכאן ולהבא mikan ulehaba and that we're looking at what does it
mean to bring a קרבן korban for a נזיר טמא nazir tamei
when you're no longer a נזיר, nazir, you know, and what elements
of the קרבן korban relate to the past and which elements relate
to the future and so on. That was not the path that
the גמרא Gemara took. Okay, let's go on now to the next
part of the משנה. Mishnah. יצא ונכנס עולה לו מן המנין. yatza
venichnas oleh lo min haminyan.
So now we've got this נזיר, nazir, we're going back to the
משנה, Mishnah, the נזיר nazir took נזירות nezirot in a cemetery, he
leaves and he comes back in, so it's עולה לו מן המנין,
oleh lo min haminyan, it counts, it's עולה מן המנין. oleh min
haminyan. Now that's bizarre. עולה מן המנין oleh min haminyan sounds like
he's collecting the number of days towards his thirty days, but that's
not true, if he leaves and goes back in, leaves and goes
back in, every time he goes back in, it starts all over
again. What do you mean he's they count towards the מנין? minyan?
So what עולה מן המנין oleh min haminyan means, because the next
line of the משנה Mishnah was, and he's חייב קרבן chayav korban
על כל אחת ואחת, al kol achat veachat, every time he basically
goes back in, or let me read the language of the משנה,
Mishnah, ואינו מביא קרבן עולה מן המנין
מביא קרבן טומאה. ve'eino mevi korban oleh min haminyan mevi korban tumah.
Right. And then by re-entering you now obligated a קרבן טומאה. korban
tumah. Right. When he becomes a נזיר טמא nazir tamei in the
cemetery, he started that way, he doesn't bring a קרבן טומאה. korban
tumah. Only when he goes out and comes in, and now he
became a נזיר טהור nazir tahor and he violated it, now he
brings a קרבן טומאה. korban tumah. So עולה מן המנין oleh min
haminyan does not mean that you start collecting days towards your thirty,
עולה מן המנין oleh min haminyan is you began your נזירות nezirot
of טהרה tahara and now if it's violated, now you will bring
a קרבן טומאה. korban tumah. Okay, but now the גמרא Gemara has
a question. Just because you walk out of a cemetery doesn't mean
you begin your נזירות nezirot of טהרה, tahara, you're still טמא. tamei.
So let's take a look.
יצא ונכנס yatza venichnas means goes in and out of the cemetery?
Yeah, leaves and then re-enters. Okay, קתני עולה לו מן המנין. katani
oleh lo min haminyan. So משום דיצא חלה נזירות? mishum deyatza chala
nezirot? What, because you step out of the cemetery, your נזירות nezirot
begins? You're still טמא. tamei. אמר שמואל כגון שיצא והזה בשלישי ובשביעי
וטבל. amar Shmuel kegon sheyatza vehiza beshlishi uvishvii vetaval. Okay, we don't
just mean he walked out. He means he left the whole scenario,
he did the sprinklings on day three and seven, he went to
the מקווה, mikvah, it means he became טהור. tahor. You started as
טמא, tamei, you walked out the cemetery, you became טהור, tahor, if
you go back in now that you're טהור, tahor, now you violated
your נזירות nezirot and you have to bring a קרבן. korban. Okay,
I don't know if that's פשט pshat in the משנה, Mishnah, but
anyway.
What, if he did it,
if he did it intentionally and with warning, yes.
Okay. וכגון דהזה vechegon dehiza twice, three and seven.
Yeah. Okay. אלא, ela, so the גמרא Gemara says fine, let's read
that into the משנה. Mishnah. But let's have another question. נכנס הוא
דעולה לו מן המנין? nichnas hu de'oleh lo min haminyan? What, only
if you enter in the cemetery does it re-enter, does it, does
it, does it start counting towards your נזירות? nezirot? לא נכנס אינו
עולה לו מן המנין? lo nichnas eino oleh lo min haminyan? What,
if you just left, it wouldn't start counting towards your נזירות, nezirot,
right? Going in doesn't start counting, it's leaving that helps you start
counting towards your נזירות. nezirot. No, so the גמרא Gemara says לא
מיבעיא קאמר. lo mibaya ka'amar. Yeah, it goes without saying. לא מיבעיא
יצא, lo mibaya yatza, certainly if you just left do you start
counting, and then you became טהור, tahor, you start counting towards your
טהרה. tahara. אלא אפילו נכנס, ela afilu nichnas, even if you re-entered,
עולה לו מן המנין, oleh lo min haminyan, it counts. Now, of
course it doesn't mean it counts, because again the phrase is funny.
עולה לו מן המנין oleh lo min haminyan means even if you
re-entered, we consider it enough that you started your נזירות nezirot that
now you'll bring a קרבן. korban. So again, the question would be
like, obvious, if you say once I left and I become טהור,
tahor, it starts the process again, so of course now that I
go in I'm going to bring a קרבן. korban. But גמרא תוספות
Gemara Tosafot says no, not necessarily, because what happens if you went
in literally let's say on day seven, right? On the exact day
that you rebegan your נזירות nezirot of טהרה, tahara, the types of
things that we were talking about. Okay, so you could say, well
that day, if it was literally the same day I became טהור
tahor and I had been טמא tamei until that point, maybe that's
just seen as one continuous state of טומאה, tumah, right? Maybe that
would not be considered like I really began my נזירות. nezirot. No,
no, no. No.
So I went and I got the ashes sprinkled, it's true, I'm
still a טבול יום tevul yom but that doesn't matter, I'm enough
טהור tahor that my נזירות nezirus of טהרה tahara begins and now,
so if you just said when you leave you begin your נזירות
nezirus of טהרה, tahara, of course when you leave you begin your
נזירות nezirus of טהרה. tahara. The חידוש chiddush is that even if
you re-entered on the very same day you became טהור tahor and
you had been טמא tamei right up until that point, so there's
only this little brief sliver of being טהור tahor in the middle,
we still say עולה לו מן המנין, oleh lo min haminyan, we
still say your נזירות nezirus began and now you've violated it and
now you have to bring a קרבן. korban. Okay, so that is
a חידוש. chiddush. Okay, אפילו נכנס עולה לו מן המנין, afilu nichnas
oleh lo min haminyan, even if you re-entered on the same day
you became טהור, tahor, we say you began your נזירות nezirus and
now you have violated it and you bring a קרבן. korban. אמר
ליה רב כהנא ורב אסי לרב, amar lei Rav Kahana veRav Assi
leRav, Rav Kahana and Rav Assi said to Rav, מאי טעמא לא
מפרשת לן כולהו הני מילי? mai taama lo mefarshet lan kulhu hanei
milei? They said like, why didn't you help, like שמואל Shmuel gave
this nice little explanation of how to read this משנה, mishnah, what
it means עולה לו מן המנין, oleh lo min haminyan, it doesn't
mean just left, it means you left and you became טהור, tahor,
it doesn't mean you only restart when you re-enter, it means that
even when you re-enter it's considered like you restart. A lot of
explanation of this משנה. mishnah. So these, they said to רב, Rav,
hey רב, Rav, we were here, you never, you didn't explain this,
we were in the ישיבה, yeshiva, why didn't you explain to us
that this is how to read this משנה? mishnah? So
אמר להון, amar lehon, he said to them, אמינא דלא צריכיתו, amina
dela tzerichitu, I thought you didn't need to understand, I thought you
understood it yourself. Why didn't you ask me? Why didn't I tell
you? Why didn't you ask me? Okay, so anyway. All
right, so that's the
explanation when you don't understand.
There
we go. Okay, רבי אליעזר אומר. Rabbi Eliezer omer. Now we get
רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: לא בו ביום. lo bo bayom.
No, no, no. If you became טמא tamei on the same day
that you became טהור, tahor, you do not bring a קרבן. korban.
You have to have been טהור tahor for two days before you
bring a קרבן. korban. Why?
שנאמר, shene'emar, because the verse says והימים הראשונים יפלו, vehayamim harishonim yipulu,
the earlier days in plural will fall away, כי טמא נזרו. ki
tamei nizro. That's when you bring a קרבן, korban, when you became
טמא tamei and there are days that will fall away, not when
you're on day one. עד שיהיו ימים ראשונים, ad sheyihyu yamim rishonim,
until there's more than one day.
So the גמרא gemara says like this, אמר עולא: amar Ulla: לא
אמר רבי אליעזר אלא בטמא שנתנזר. lo amar Rabbi Eliezer ela betamei
shenitnazar. When is it that he requires there to be two days,
you to be in day two for to be obligated a קרבן?
korban? That's only if you started בטומאה. betumah. Okay, אבל בנזיר טהור
שנטמא, aval benazir tahor shenitma,
if you started בטהרה betaharah and you accepted נזירות nezirus as a
נזיר טהור nazir tahor and then on that day became טמא, tamei,
אפילו יום אחד סותר. afilu yom echad soter. There he would agree
to the רבנן rabbanan that even on the very same day it
is, you know, you bring the קרבן korban and you do not
need two days. So what's the reason to distinguish? Why, what's the
logic? I mean, if he says ימים ראשונים, yamim rishonim, why would
he distinguish between whether you started off as being טמא tamei or
started off as being טהור? tahor? So אמר רבא, amar Rava, מאי
טעמא דרבי אליעזר, mai taama deRabbi Eliezer, what's the reason of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer based on this limited read of רבי אליעזר? Rabbi
Eliezer? דאמר קרא, de'amar kra, the verse says כי טמא נזרו. ki
tamei nizro.
It says והימים הראשונים יפלו, vehayamim harishonim yipulu,
the earlier days will fall away, from which we learn that there
have to be multiple days that are falling away, כי טמא נזרו,
ki tamei nizro, which he's reading as not because you have now
violated your נזירות, nezirus, but משום דבטומאה נזר, mishum debetumah nazar, because
כי טמא נזרו, ki tamei nizro, your whole נזירות nezirus began בטומאה.
betumah. You getting it? We're reading the פסוק pasuk כי טמא נזרו
ki tamei nizro as our case of being a נזיר בבית הקברות.
nazir bevet hakevarot. והימים הראשונים יפלו, vehayamim harishonim yipulu, you now bring
a קרבן korban when you've lost multiple days in a case where
כי טמא נזרו, ki tamei nizro, your נזירות nezirus started בטומאה. betumah.
Okay, so it's a very interesting read of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you need two days. What's bothering the
גמרא gemara seems to be why did he only say this in
a משנה mishnah about starting off your נזירות nezirus in a cemetery?
Just say it generally, a נזיר nazir who becomes טמא, tamei, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you only bring your קרבן korban if you
became טמא tamei on day two. Why not say that? Why talk
about being in a cemetery? So the גמרא gemara is saying maybe
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said the idea of multiple days only when
you began בטומאה. betumah. Only then, you know, that's when we said
that you would need to have two days to your credit before
you're obligated in a קרבן. korban. If you started בטומאה, betumah, maybe
you need to get more established your footing as a נזיר טהור
nazir tahor and be into your second day. If you started בטהרה,
betaharah, then you bring it even after your first day. You can
understand the logic. You start בטהרה, betaharah, there's a clear immediate violation
even on the first day. You start בטומאה, betumah, you know, maybe
you're still in that sort of shadow of being טמא tamei and
you have to more thoroughly establish yourself as טהור tahor before you
bring second day and that's now explaining why he says that in
the משנה, mishnah, only in the case of starting in a cemetery
and how we read it from the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so now
the גמרא gemara says like this: איתיביה אביי, eitivei Abaye, Abaye asked
on this idea: הריני נזיר מאה יום, hareini nazir me'ah yom, somebody
says I'm a נזיר nazir for a hundred days on this idea
that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer limits himself to the case of starting
in a cemetery. Okay, let's take a look. הריני נזיר מאה יום,
hareini nazir me'ah yom, a guy says I'm a נזיר nazir for
a hundred days, ונטמא
בתחילה, venitma betechilah, בתחילת מאה, betechilat me'ah, and he becomes טמא tamei
on day one. One. יכול Yachol יהא yehei סותר? soter? Maybe that
would destroy, meaning and he'd have to bring a קרבן? korban? תלמוד
Talmud לומר lomar והימים vehayamim הראשונים harishonim יפלו. yipolu. And the earlier
days will fall away. עד Ad שיהיו sheyihyu לו lo ימים yamim
ראשונים. rishonim. You have to have multiple days. So this is we
could just stop right here. You see how this contradicts the point
that was just made. It says a person accepted a נזירות nezirut
of a hundred days, okay, it's not say that he started as
a נזיר nazir טמא, tamei, and it says the first of those
days, if he becomes טמא, tamei, he does not he doesn't bring
a קרבן. korban. He would have to be only day two. It
quotes this פסוק, pasuk, right? So you see very clearly that רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says his position not in a special case, in
any case, every case. It's only when there are multiple days, only
when you're on day two, is that when we sort of say
that you bring a קרבן. korban.
But why do you need the hundred? It could just be...
I know, because that's true, but that's the case and we're going
to see that's continuing reading the ברייתא. Baraisa. Okay. עד Ad שיהיו
sheyihyu לו lo ימים yamim ראשונים rishonim וזה vezeh אין ein לו
lo ראשונים. rishonim. And this one does not have multiple early days.
He's only on day one. נטמא Nitma בסוף besof מאה. me'ah. Let's
say he became טמא tamei on the last day. יכול Yachol יהא
yehei סותר? soter? Maybe if you became טמא tamei on the very
last day, you'd have to go and do another full hundred days?
תלמוד Talmud לומר lomar והימים vehayamim הראשונים harishonim יפלו. yipolu. Early the
earlier days fall away. מכלל Michlal דאיכא deika אחרונים. acharonim. If there
are earlier ones, there are also future ones. Okay? So you're in
some middle day here. The fact that it says ראשונים rishonim doesn't
say all the days fall away, it says the earlier ones. So
does that right so that means that there are some that are
still yet to come. So therefore that idea that it all falls
away is not on day one and not on the last day.
Okay? וזה Vezeh יש yesh לו lo ראשונים rishonim ואחרונים? va'acharonim? Okay
now, this I'm sorry, תלמוד Talmud לומר lomar והימים vehayamim הראשונים harishonim
יפלו yipolu מכלל michlal דאיכא deika אחרונים acharonim וזה vezeh אין ein
לו lo אחרונים. acharonim. And this one does not have last days.
נטמא Nitma ביום beyom מאה me'ah חסר chasar אחת. achat. What's day
99? יכול Yachol יהא yehei סותר? soter? Maybe it would not
destroy the earlier days? תלמוד Talmud לומר lomar והימים vehayamim הראשונים harishonim
יפלו, yipolu, מכלל Michlal דאיכא deika אחרונים. acharonim. So there have to
be earlier days which there are and there have to be later
days which there are. וזה Vezeh יש yesh לו lo ראשונים rishonim
ואחרונים. va'acharonim. Okay, now this explains why he gave the example of
a hundred days because you might remember this is the position of
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, the same רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says
you need multiple early days, if the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that
says that if you became טמא tamei on your last day, you
don't start it all over again, but you do but what he
does say is, you might remember this, that if you became טמא
tamei on your last day, you have to do thirty days more.
It says it says ביום beyom מלאות... m'lot... what is it...
זאת Zot תורת torat הנזיר hanazir ביום beyom מלאות m'lot ימי yemei
נזרו, nezro, something like that. So it says if the תורה Torah
of the נזיר nazir means a standard נזירות nezirut of thirty days,
ביום beyom מלאות, m'lot, that's what will apply to you if you
became טמא tamei on the final day, on the יום yom מלאות,
m'lot, the day that filled out the number. So this is the
point. He does say that if you become טמא tamei on the
last day, it doesn't destroy everything, but it does mean thirty more
days. So if you're a standard נזיר, nazir, there's no difference between
that. I became נזיר nazir on day thirty, okay, I don't lose
all the earlier days, I just have to do thirty more days.
Same point, I have to do thirty days. But if you're a
נזיר nazir for a hundred days, then it makes a difference. If
you became טמא tamei on day 99, you gotta do a hundred
days. If you became טמא tamei on day a hundred, you don't
have to do a hundred days, you only have to do thirty
days. Okay, so that's the position. If you became טמא tamei on
the first day, you don't start over again, you don't bring a
קרבן, korban, and if you became טמא tamei on the last day,
well, you bring a קרבן, korban, but you don't have to start
all over again, you only have to do thirty more days.
Yes. I thought that, maybe I misread this, I thought it would
have to be the 98th day because ימים yamim ראשונים rishonim ואחרונים?
va'acharonim?
Oh, so that's a good question that תוספות Tosafot asks about whether
the ימים yamim would mean that there have to
be...
maybe two? Right, so that's a good question, because but it does
say it says מאה me'ah חסר chasar אחת. achat. So there are
ימים yamim because there's the remainder of day 99 and there's day
a hundred. The same way when it was day two, you had
the part of day one that you were a נזיר nazir and
the part of day two that you're in. It doesn't need to
be any full days, right? But so but it is parallel. I
do want to say one other thing about the word יפלו, yipolu,
because I've been focusing on the idea of do you bring a
קרבן? korban? But that's really not the language that's being used. The
language that's being used is, right, is it סותר? soter? So that
which is exactly the focus, by the way, when you become טמא
tamei on day a hundred. When you become טמא tamei on day
a hundred, you bring a קרבן, korban, okay? It's only saying that
because you don't have אחרונים, acharonim, it's not סותר, soter, you don't
lose the whole hundred. You only lose you only have to do
let's say another thirty like we said. But if that's true, now
apply that idea to becoming טמא tamei on day one. You become
טמא tamei on day one, and it says it's not סותר. soter.
So what does that mean when it says it's not סותר? soter?
It sounds like it's actually saying, and this is really bizarre try
to get your head around this, that I became a נזיר טהור
nazir tahor. today, I became טמא tamei today, okay, after I go
through a טהרה taharah process, I only have 29 days left. I
don't have to do another thirty. Right? Which seems like, what? Like
I became at the I didn't even have a full day to
my credit. I became טמא tamei on that day, right? So what
do you mean it's not סותר? soter? Fine, it's not סותר, soter,
but it shouldn't be עולה, oleh, right? I don't have anything to
my credit. So it's not clear if that's what's being said, but
there is תוספות Tosafot that sort of discusses that idea. Does it
really mean I get to count day one to my credit, you
know, because I didn't have two days yet? So it's easier to
understand that the point when you became טמא tamei on day one
is to say you don't bring a קרבן, korban, and the point
when you become טמא tamei on day 100 is to say you
do bring a קרבן korban but you don't start all the 100
days again. But again they're being talked about in parallel, so it's
a little funny to give those different interpretations. Yes.
I like that you emphasized the word יפלו. yipelu. I don't know
what to make of it, but the metaphor of the words סותר
sotair and יפלו yipelu is like in הלכות שבת. Hilchot Shabbat. It's
like building a wall. Each day is a brick. You have to
have a certain number for the thing to fall down. Right. That's
a nice idea.
Yeah, yeah, it's a nice idea.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. So now we all brought in that fascinating ברייתא. braita. Now
the גמרא Gemara is going to show that this shows that רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says his position even by a נזיר טהור. nazir
tahor, דהא, Deha, says the גמרא, Gemara, בטמא שנזר לא מצי אמרת.
betamei shenazar lo matzi amrat. This ברייתא braita cannot be talking about
a person who is טמא tamei except in נזירות. neziroot. מכדי תני,
Mikdi tani, הריני נזיר מאה, Harei ni nazir meiah, ונטמא בתחילת מאה.
venitma betichlat meiah.
He says I'm a נזיר nazir for 100 and says that you
became טמא tamei at the beginning of that 100. So it sounds
like you went right from your נדר neder to the problem of
becoming טמא, tamei, so it sounded like you were טהור tahor to
begin with. Okay, so we're talking about a guy who was טהור.
tahor וקתני, Vekatani, עד שלא היו ימים ראשונים, ad shelo hayu yamim
rishonim, and it says that day one is not a problem. It
needs to be on day two. Even if you started with being
טהור. tahor. תיובתא. Tiyuvta. So that shows a contradiction to this attempt
to limit רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer to the case of the guy
being in the graveyard. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says even for a
normal guy, it's only a problem when you become טמא tamei on
day two. But again the question is what does that mean? Does
it mean only then do you bring a קרבן? korban? That's the
emphasis of the משנה. mishna. And that to me just seems to
be necessary because again I could get that you say that less
than that it's not סותר, sotair, but it can't be עולה. oleh.
How does a guy who became טמא tamei on day one get
to count day one? Okay, so I'm going to say that for
the first case it's the question of do you bring a קרבן.
korban. For the question about the end of the period, it seems
that the bigger question is do you have to restart the whole
thing or not, and there you don't restart the whole thing on
the last day, you only have to do 30. Now the גמרא
Gemara has one last question.
אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי. Amar lei Rav Pappa le-Abaye. Rav Pappa
said to Abaye, הני ימים דקאמרינן, Hani yamim deka amrinan, the days
when we said that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer needs two days, דנפק
חד ומתחיל תרין? denafak chad umatchil tarein? Does it mean that you
did one day, day one of being a נזיר nazir טהור, tahor.
and now day two began and you became טמא tamei on day
two? So that's days. There was the part of day one, you
accepted your נזירות neziroot at 1 PM, whatever was left of day
one, and whatever began day two before you became טמא. tamei. Okay,
או דלמא, o dilma, or do we say, דנפקי תרין ומתחיל תלתא?
denafki tarein umatchil tlata? No, to have days at least one of
them maybe has to be a full day. You had the part
of day one, you had all of day two that you were
טהור, tahor, and then you became טמא tamei on day three. So
does the idea of days require at least one of them to
be a full day? לא הוה בידיה. Lo hava beyadeih. He didn't
have the answer. אתא שייליה לרבא. Ata sheila le-Rava. They went and
asked Rava. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, Rava said, יפלו כתיב. yipelu ketiv. It says יפלו.
yipelu. Well, that answers it. So תוספות Tosafot says somehow
the word יפלו, yipelu, I don't know where we get this, but
it means that they just fell away, somehow signifies that it wasn't
so significant, that it was relatively trivial the amount of days that
were falling away, and therefore it means you didn't need a full
day. Even a partial day one and a partial day two is
enough. Again, I don't get how he gets it from the פסוק.
pasuk. All right, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara now says.
ואיצטריך למכתב ימים ואיצטריך למכתב יפלו. Ve-itztarich lemichtav yamim ve-itztarich lemichtav yipelu.
It needs to say ימים yamim which helps me two, and it
needs to say יפלו yipelu which somehow I learn mean even during
the second day. דאי כתב רחמנא ימים ולא יפלו, De-i ketav Rachmana
yamim velo yipelu, if it had just said ימים yamim without יפלו
yipelu which somehow is minimizing the amount of days, הוה אמינא עד
דנפקי תרין ומתחיל תלתא. hava amina ad denafki tarein umatchil tlata. I
would have thought like the הוה אמינא. hava amina. You need to
have a full second day and it's only a problem when the
third day begins, when at least one of those days was full.
כתב רחמנא יפלו. Katav Rachmana yipelu. So it has to say יפלו
yipelu with somehow that they just fall away. That's enough, even on
day two it's a problem. This is according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer.
ואי כתב יפלו ולא כתב ימים, Ve-i ketav yipelu velo ketav yamim,
but if it had said יפלו yipelu and didn't say ימים, yamim,
הוה אמינא אפילו חד. hava amina afilu chad.
I would have said even one day. So why does it say
יפלו? yipelu? זה? zeh? Yes, somehow we're talking in the generic, they,
but we don't mean concretely specifically multiply. So therefore כתב רחמנא ימים
katav Rachmana yamim so that you know no, no, no, we really
mean that there has to be at least two days. All of
this is according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says that only when a נזיר nazir becomes טמא tamei on day
two does he bring a קרבן. korban. On day one he does
not. And because you need ימים, yamim, days, but ימים yamim doesn't
have to be full days as long as you're into day two,
that's enough. And that also goes back to the point of why
day 99 satisfies that criteria, because you have the remainder of day
99 and all of day 100 and that is sufficient. That's all
according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, okay, who says that you need
multiple days. Yes.
There's no one would ever think that יפלו yipelu plural could mean
one day.
To then עד כדי כך ad kedei kach require that the פסוק
pasuk says ימים.
yamim. I don't know what to say about that. That's really far.
I know, I know.
All right, I don't know what to say about that. Let's go
to the next משנה. mishna. מי שנזר נזירות הרבה. Mi shenazar nezirot
harbe. Now, this is the use of the word הרבה harbe here
is a little distracting. הרבה Harbe here does not mean multiple נזירות.
nezirot.
It's not נזירות הרבה, nezirot harbe, it's נזירות הרבה, neziroot harbe, a
big נזירות. neziroot. It's really like נזירות גדולה neziroot gedola or something.
Okay, it's a very it's large, it's much bigger than a normal.
So, somebody sets it for a hundred days or for ten years
or whatever it is. והשלים את נזירותו V'hishlim et neziroto and he
finished, he did his year of נזירות. neziroot. ואחרי כן בא לארץ
V'acharei ken ba la'aretz and now he's coming to the land of
Israel because he has to bring his קרבן. korban. Now he wants
to wrap it up. He did he put in his year. בית
שמאי אומרים, Beit Shammai omrim, נזיר שלושים יום. nazir shloshim yom.
It's nice that you came to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you have
to do another thirty days. It's a big encouragement to make עליה,
aliyah, right? Come make עליה, aliyah, we'll extend your נזירות neziroot for
thirty days. בית הלל, Beit Hillel, ha, they do בית שמאי Beit
Shammai one better. אומרים נזיר בתחילה, Omrim nazir batchila, you have to
start all over again! So much for בית הלל Beit Hillel being
the מיקל. meikil. Okay, you come to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you
put in your year of נזירות, neziroot, another year. Now, the guy
doesn't have a choice because what's he going to do? Stay in
חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz and he'll never end his נזירות. neziroot. Now,
so very strange like what is this? Now, you know, so it
could be what we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, but well, you
know, I won't.
מצוה תלויה בארץ? Mitzvah teluya ba'aretz?
No, no, but no, no, no, but you have to come to
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael in order in order to bring the קרבן.
korban. No, it seems that it's because it gets to this whole
idea which בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai talk
about a lot, which is טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah issues and that
there's an idea that חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz has טומאת ארץ העמים.
tumat eretz ha'amim. So therefore, what we're essentially saying, and this is
why it comes at the heel of the discussion of being a
נזיר nazir בבית הקברות. bebeit hakevarot. You're becoming a נזיר nazir in
חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, you know what that's like? That's like you're
being a נזיר nazir in a בית הקברות. beit hakevarot. Okay, I
mean we're not saying that, but I think that's suggested by the
juxtaposition, right? There's this טומאת ארץ העמים tumat eretz ha'amim partly because
it's just an attitude towards outside of Israel, and because there's a
sense that, you know, who knows, the non-Jews buried their bodies in
all places. So you're basically in a type of an almost a
בית הקברות. beit hakevarot. So only when you come to ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael can we say, ah, now you're really דכייא, dachya, now
you're really starting your true נזירות של טהרה, neziroot shel taharah, you
have to start all over again. That's בית הלל. Beit Hillel. That's
what בית הלל Beit Hillel says. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says we'll
just do it symbolically, thirty days. We're not going to really require
the whole thing again. Yes.
Does for the purposes of this טומאה tumah of a נזיר, nazir,
is the corpse of a non-Jew the same as?
Yes. No, the same as a טומאת מת. tumat meit. The only
difference between a corpse of a non-Jew and a corpse of a
Jew
is
whether it conducts the טומאה tumah by אוהל ohel or only by
touch. But in terms of this הלכה, halacha, it's the same, it's
the same issue. In terms of violating the טומאה tumah of the
נזיר nazir and all of that, same for כהנים, Kohanim, violating their
טומאה, tumah, doesn't matter, Jew, non-Jew corpse. That's only a question of
how the טומאה tumah is conducted.
So, and this is a very seems like a very naive question,
but if I'm in a בית הקברות, beit hakevarot, so what's that
טומאה? tumah? It's not טומאת אוהל. tumat ohel.
Yes, it is. If you're on top of the corpse, it's אוהל.
ohel. You are being מאהיל ma'ahil on top,
you're right.
But if non-Jews don't have the issue of אוהל, ohel, then who's,
like, why would we assume that we're touching the corpses of non-Jews?
Right, so that's a very good question, right? Because that's absolutely correct.
I understand the question.
If there's no טומאת אוהל tumat ohel by non-Jews, then unless who
cares if you're in a בית הקברות beit hakevarot of non-Jews? Right,
so that's actually true, and so there could be a couple of
points to that. Number one, which is why, by the way, in
all these discussions, oh, if you're taking a, flying in a plane
and it takes off right near a cemetery, is there a problem
if you're a כהן? Kohen? It's really primarily a problem like in
New York where there's Jewish cemeteries.
So there's a couple of answers. One answer is first of all
there's a position that even non-Jews are
מטמא באוהל. metamei b'ohel. Okay, but there are some people that are
חושש choshesh for that position and so on, so maybe that's the
idea going around in the גמרא. Gemara. The other possibility could be
concern about like what the גמרא Gemara does have concerns about, about
like little bits of bone and other types of things that would
be on the surface, not everything is always buried as deep and
stays as buried as you want it to be. That seems to
be a pretty prevalent concern in the גמרא. Gemara. And the third
idea is that this issue about טומאת ארץ העמים tumat eretz ha'amim
is a mixture of a concern of real טומאה tumah of corpses
and of an attitude of חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. So it's somehow
those two are reinforcing. So it's not all the technical aspects, which
is why it's only a טומאה דרבנן, tumah d'rabbanan, which is why
this discussion of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai
is only מדרבנן, m'drabbanan, and it's symbolically you have to start your
נזירות neziroot again because it's like you were in a בית הקברות,
beit hakevarot, there was a טומאה, tumah, but halachically you could totally
bring your קרבן korban now and fulfill your obligation דאורייתא d'oraisa and
so on as long as you didn't come in contact with a
corpse in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, you're fine. Okay, but רבנן, rabbanan,
that we sort of treat it that way and we make you
start again, or for בית שמאי Beit Shammai at least do something
symbolic, thirty days. Yes.
Do we have anywhere if you're in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael as
a נזיר nazir and leave?
Right, so the same thing. If you're a כהן, Kohen, for example,
you're not supposed to leave ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Same idea, right?
And by the way, that's an important similarity, right? That a כהן
Kohen and a נזיר nazir both can't drink wine when you're in
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, can't become טמא למת, tamei l'meit, and
so on. So there is that, a נזיר nazir is sort of.
trying to be a כהן Kohen without being in the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, trying to sort of be at that level of קדושה.
kedushah. But both of them are not allowed to leave ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael for חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, but if they do, they
haven't violated their status דאורייתא, de'oraisa, right? It's a דרבנן derabbanan type
of an idea. Okay, so if you're a נזיר nazir and you
leave and you leave, oh, you're saying within this הלכה. halacha. Oh
you're not saying like דאורייתא. de'oraisa. Once we've established that if you're
in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz and you come in, you have to
do it again, if you're in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and you
go out and come back in, would you have to do it
again? That's a good question. I'm not sure. I mean, it's not
in the גמרא Gemara on this משנה, Mishnah, so I don't know,
I'd have to see about that.
Unless it's necessarily
symbolic, especially in the נזיר שלשים יום. nazir shloshim yom.
You could say it's kind of like a הקינת הגבורה hakinat hagevura
that, yeah, I'm a נזיר nazir and for that you need to
do 30 days in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Part of the 10
years, you know, that was because you were in חוץ לארץ chutz
la'aretz when you said it, so that part.
But why would we say that you're... I mean like, yeah, I
don't know why we would interpret it that way. Okay,
let's see what
the משנה Mishnah says. Okay, מעשה בהלני
המלכה,
Maaseh be'Helni
HaMalka, story with Queen הלני. Helni. Charlie, remind us who הלני המלכה
Helni HaMalka was.
Oh, she was the ruler of a tributary state to the Parthian
Empire, Persian Empire, who converted to
Judaism with her family.
And where, what state was she the ruler of?
Adiabene is what the Greeks called it. It was like in around
northwest Iraq today.
Northwest Iraq.
מונבז Munbaz is his son...
מונבז, Munbaz, I think was the name of her husband
or son.
Alright, there you go.
Wealthy Adiabene and
she was very wealthy.
Okay, so מעשה בהלני המלכה, Maaseh be'Helni HaMalka, story with Queen, this
Queen הלני, Helni, who converted to Judaism. שהלך בנה למלחמה, Shehalach benah
lamilchamah,
her son went out to war. ואמרה, Ve'amrah, אם יבוא בני מן
המלחמה בשלום, im yavo beni min hamilchamah beshalom, if my son returns
from war in peace, הרי נזירה שבע שנים, harei nezirah sheva shanim,
I will be a נזירה nezirah for seven years. So here you
get this exact, like, it's also powerful and seems almost like saying
why do people accept the vow, right? This whole idea we've even
seen by bargaining with God has been like a theme, but it
has never been as explicit as this משנה. Mishnah. Right, I mean
you know, but that goes back all the way to יעקב. Yaakov.
אם אלקים עמדי, Im Elokim imadi, ושמרני בדרך הזאת, ushmarani baderech hazos,
כל אשר תתן לי, kol asher titein li, etc. ובא בנה מן
המלחמה, U'va benah min hamilchamah,
and her son returned. ועשתה נזירה שבע שנים, Ve'astah nezirah sheva shanim,
so she fulfilled her vow for seven years she was a נזירה.
nezirah. ובסוף שבע שנים, U'vesof sheva shanim,
and in the end of seven years,
עלתה לארץ, alsah la'aretz, she made עליה. Aliyah. והורוה בית הלל שתהא
נזירה עוד שבע שנים אחרות. Vehoruha Beis Hillel shetihi nezirah od sheva
shanim acheros. Ah, what a good קירוב kiruv pro-tip!
So בית הלל Beis Hillel said, oh great, welcome to ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, seven more years. Okay.
ובסוף שבע שנים נטמאת, U'vesof sheva shanim nitmeis, and then at the
end of that other seven years, it's almost like a יעקב Yaakov
and רחל Rochel and לאה Leah story. The first seven years, another
seven years, and then at the end of that seven years, the
very last day, she became טמאה. tmeiah. ונמצאת נזירה עשרים ואחת שנה,
Venimtzes nezirah esrim ve'achas shanah, and as she has to do another
seven years because she was,
so therefore it's 21 years. Wait, so the whole seven? I mean,
she had been keeping 14 but was only obligated in seven. She
kept a second seven, but we don't consider it a 14-year נזירות.
nezirus. It was a seven-year נזירות nezirus that she had to do
again, and now she becomes... אחרונים? acharonim?
It was the very last day?
I don't know, we're not doing this with רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
So maybe she should פסקן pasken like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, and
maybe it was two days before the end. Okay, ונמצאת נזירה עשרים
ואחת שנה. venimtzes nezirah esrim ve'achas shanah. אמר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbi
Yehuda, says רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, לא הייתה נזירה אלא ארבע עשרה
שנה. lo haysah nezirah ela arba esreh shanah. No
no no, it was only 14 years. So the question is, does
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda agree with בית הלל Beis Hillel but say
she didn't become טמאה? tmeiah? All right, so that's just an interesting
different version of the story. She didn't become טמאה, tmeiah, it was
only 14. Or is he saying, no, she did become טמאה tmeiah
and it was 14, but I don't agree with you בית הלל,
Beis Hillel, I don't think she had to do seven for making
עליה. Aliyah. She did seven and then seven again for becoming טמאה,
tmeiah, but not because she came to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So
this is a very fascinating question about how much you have to
start again when you come to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Seems like
a little, I don't know, disincentive, although the alternative is worse, you
stay in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, you never get out of this.
What's the second possibility, when did she become טמאה? tmeiah?
She became טמאה tmeiah in the end of... at the end of
seven, and so she did another seven.
That has nothing to do with ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Right, so maybe he's just saying, yeah, she came to ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael but I hold like בית שמאי Beis Shammai and she
only did 30 days and then, you know, but then she had
to do another seven, but not... it wasn't 21. Okay, so the
גמרא's Gemara going to talk about both of those possibilities. We will
see this tomorrow. Yep.